Lawrence Kupferman Papers
Lawrence Kupferman Papers
circa 1947-1964
Kupferman, Lawrence, 1909-
1.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter, etcher. Died 1982. Correspondence, financial material, photographs and slides of work, sketchbooks, and printed material, including articles and exhibition catalogs.
149116
Biographical History
Lawrence Kupferman (1909-1982) was an American painter and etcher. Born in Boston, Massachusetts, he studied at the Boston Museum School (1929-1931) and at the Massachusetts School of Art (1931-1935), and like many of his fellow artists of the time was employed by the Work's Progress Administration (1937-1940). He taught at the Massachusetts College of Art for many years, eventually becoming head of the Department of Painting.
Kupferman's work has been exhibited at such distinguished venues as the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, the 1939 World's Fair in New York, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Art Institute of Chicago, the Museum of Modern Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and the Baltimore Museum of Art, among others, and is in the permanent collections of many prestigious institutions including the British Museum, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Museum of Modern Art, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Museum of Fine Arts Boston, the Fogg Art Musuem and the Brooklyn Museum.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Lawrence Kupferman Papers contains correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, photographs, and printed material.
Correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing. Incoming correspondence is divided into business and personal correspondence. Subject files contain lists, bills, receipts, and a contract. Manuscripts consists mainly of sketchbooks and two original poems. Photographs contains glass slides of paintings and some works. Published material contains clippings and other miscellany.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is divided into incoming and outgoing; incoming is arranged alphabetically by sender while outgoing is arranged chronologically. The remaining series are arranged alphabetically by type or title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Kupferman, Lawrence Edward, 1909-1982.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Etchers -- United States.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Sketchbooks.; Slides (photographs); Artists.; Etchers.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Business
      - B-S (Box 1)
      - Ruth White Gallery (Box 1)
    - Personal
      - A-S (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - 1956-1964 (Box 1)
    - Letters to Charlie (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Artist-dealer contract (Box 1)
  - Bills and receipts (Box 1)
  - Lists (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Sketch books (Box 1)
  - Two original poems: "Old House Brewster" and "Truro Beach" (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Glass slides - paintings (Box 1)
  - Works
    - Oct 1949 - May 1950 (Box 1)
    - Oct and Nov 1947, Oct 1949, Dec 1947-Jan 1948 (Box 2)
    - 1947, Feb-May 1948, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Kupferman's paintings, 1963; 1964,; undated (Box 2)
- Published material
  - Articles about (Box 2)
  - Exhibitions, Kupferman and others (Box 2)
  - "Ehec", paint manual (Box 2)
  - News clipping, "Resin compoubd defies elements", paint manual (Box 2)